原视频名：SpaceX Starship Number 9 Makes Perfect* Flight
(*except for the landing which was a huge fireball)
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/zwZl6YV3xYA
原视频发布日期：20210203
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
可以参考Scott谈Starship SN8
b23.tv/av885679523
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
And by now you've probably heard that SpaceX did their second high altitude test flight for Starship.
现在你可能已经听说了SpaceX为Starship进行了第二次高空试飞
This was Starship SN9.
这是Starship SN9
It had been ready to go after SN8 crashed and burned.
SN8坠毁后 它就已经准备好了
But had been held up
但被耽搁了
by a combination of SpaceX's lean development process
这之中包括SpaceX的倾斜 式开发过程
engine problems and the FAA approvals.
发动机练坏了 以及美国联邦航空局的批准问题
But we'll talk about that later.
但我们稍后再谈这个问题
By now you've probably heard the landing didn't go as planned.
现在你可能已经听说了着陆没有按计划进行
This is what happened.
事情的经过是这样的
The vehicle was in the horizontal descent orientation.
航天器是在水平下降的姿态上
It tried to light two engines to perform the landing burn but only one lit.
它试图启动两台发动机进行着陆点火 但只有一台开机了
It lost control and ended up crashing at about 200 kilometers per hour 120 miles per hour.
失控 并最终以200公里每小时或120英里每小时的速度坠毁
If you look at photos of the pad after this, there's a lot less debris left on the pad.
如果你看这之后的着陆场的照片 着陆场上留下的碎片就少了很多
But if you look at that white cloud there,
但如果你看那片白云的话
that is liquid oxygen in the header tank
那是头部储箱中的液氧
and one of the cool ways we know this is well the slow motion footage.
这能通过慢动作视频这样很棒的方法看出
But one of the tank watchers Lab Padre has a thermal camera
但其中一个储罐观察者Lab Padre有一台热像仪
and this is normally great because you can see the tank filling
通常来讲 这在观察燃料加注上面很有帮助
but when you see this landing, you see the hot area for the explosion.
但当你(用热像仪)看着陆的时候 你会看到爆炸的热区
And the black area on the right as the liquid oxygen spills everywhere and reduces the temperature.
而右边则存在着黑色的区域 因为液氧到处泼洒 降低了温度
Also note the mushroom cloud actually rising up.
也能注意到上升中的蘑菇云
This wasn't a nuclear explosion but this was a pretty big boom.
这不是核爆炸 但也是相当大的爆炸了
And as it turns out a big boom was one of the reasons why this launch took so long to get approved by the FAA.
而事实证明 大爆炸也是这次发射花了这么长时间才得到FAA批准的原因之一
According to the FAA SpaceX for the SN8 flight
根据FAA SpaceX为SN8飞行提供的资料显示
they were supposed to request a waiver to allow them to fly this
他们应该申请豁免 以允许他们进行试飞
without actually doing the math doing the investigation about the effects of the blast.
而没有真正进行计算和调查 关于爆炸的影响
They flew without doing that
还没这么做就飞了
and the FAA said no you guys have to do
FAA说 不 你们必须这样做
like we have to do a whole investigation into your entire safety culture
也就是我们要对你的整个安全文化做一个完整的调查一样
because we think it's bad that you would consider launching without actually getting proper approval.
因为我们认为 在没有实际得到适当的批准之前进行发射 是很糟糕的
And it's worth breaking out google maps here just to get a lay of the land.
那么值得一提的是 我们可以用谷歌地图看下这周围的地形
And so this is the area. You can see SpaceX launch facility down there in Boca Chica state park.
那么 这一块你可以看到SpaceX设立在博卡奇卡州立公园的发射设施
It's on an area that's it's basically a like an island connected by a road.
这地方基本上就像是由公路连接的岛屿
And you'll actually if you look at the map in detail
而你实际上 如果你看地图的细节
you'll find there's a lot of people that drive out there in cars
你会发现那里有很多人开车兜风
so they have to clear that out whenever they are having a launch.
所以 SpaceX必须确保在发射时把那里腾空
And the sheriffs will set up a roadblock on this roadway.
县治安官会在这条路上设置路障
Now the nearest sort of urban area is up north that's the South Padre Island there.
那么 最近的城市地区是北边的南帕德雷岛
That's on on the other side of the shipping channel.
那是在航道的另一边
There are actually a lot of cameras from the tank watchers up on that island.
岛上有很多储罐观察者的摄像头
But there are actually closer residents.
但其实还有更近的居民
There's a village right next to the SpaceX construction facility and tracking station.
在SpaceX建造设施和跟踪站的旁边有一个村庄
And this was Boca Chica village.
而这就是博卡奇卡村
And because it's so close to where they were testing stuff,
因为这里离他们测试的地方很近
SpaceX has been trying to buy these people out of their homes
SpaceX一直想把这些人花钱赶走
so that they can essentially take control of the area
这样 他们就可以基本上控制这个地区了
and not have to evacuate people every time they're performing a test with the potential for explosions.
而不必每次在进行有可能发生爆炸的测试时 都要疏散人员
But there are a few people who have resisted their financial incentives
但也有少数人抵制了他们的金钱诱惑
and they play host to a whole bunch of cameras in their backyards
而在自己的后院里装了一大堆的摄像机
which let us see these kind of views.
以让我们看到这些视角
And while we're admiring this, look there's four different stainless steel pressurized things there.
当我们在欣赏这个景象的时候 可以看到那里有四个不同的不锈钢加压储罐
I mean we've got SN9 on the right purging its engines ready to go.
我是指 在右边 我们能看到SN9(Scott口胡)在预冷它的发动机 准备发射
There's the test tank SN7, SN10 standing vertical
(旁边)那是SN7测试储罐 以及竖立着的SN10
and in the middle of the tanks is hoppy there
而在储罐中间的则是跳跳 (指Starhopper)
which is now where they mount all of the cameras and radars and things like this.
现在他们在跳跳身上装满了摄像头和雷达之类的东西
So I believe this camera is attached to hoppy.
那么我相信这台摄像机是安装在跳跳上的
And the great thing about this angle is
而这个角度的好处是
you can see the undersides of SN10 which is closest to us an SN9 which is further away.
你可以看到离我们最近的SN10和更远的SN9的底部
And you can see the black patches where they are testing the thermal protection tiles.
你可以看到黑色的斑点 也就是正在测试的隔热瓦
Now for these small hops they're not going fast enough that they need thermal protection.
那么它们只跳这么点的高度 所产生的速度还没有快到需要做隔热的程度
But what they're just doing is
但他们正在做的是
they're testing the tiles will remain fixed to the surface using the pins.
要测试这些隔热瓦能否使用插销固定在表面
And by the way spoiler I don't think there's many tiles left attached to SN9.
那么顺便剧透一下 我觉得SN9上面贴着的隔热瓦应该已经没留下几片了
So anyway fast forward to the actual flight.
那么不管这些了 快进到实际的试飞中
There was a bit of a pause in the clock at 13 seconds but they continued.
在倒计时到13秒的时候有一点停顿 但他们继续
We got the signature three vent squirt and the all three engines lit and SN9 started.
我们看到了标志性的三个排气口喷气的景象 之后 三台发动机全部点火 SN9起飞了
It ascent towards the target of 10 kilometers.
它朝着10公里的目标高度上升
That's what they had been authorized to do for this flight.
这就是他们被授权进行这次飞行的高度
So obviously for a test flight taking off from the pad,
那么很明显 一次从发射场起飞的试飞
they have to use a lower propellant load than you would normally get in a fully loaded Starship.
他们必须使用较少的推进剂 而不是通常情况下加满燃料的Starship
This will have to have the header tanks because need to perform transition maneuver
因为需要进行(机腹翻转的)过渡机动 所以头部储箱必须有推进剂加注
but there's a great shot showing all three of the engines lit up.
但是这个镜头很好 拍下了三台发动机全部点火的状态
And they also included some on-board cameras including this one off the bay.
直播中还包含了一些箭上摄像头视角 包括这个安装在舱外的摄像头
See that. That is Raptor number 49. Also note some flickering flames
看到了吗？那是49号猛禽 还有一些闪烁的火焰
and over on the top right of that camera there's some flapping panels there.
在摄像头的右上方有一些挡板
Those are thermal protection materials that are protecting things like pressure vessels inside the skirt
这些都是保护裙板内的压力容器等设备的热保护材料
and those are important later because I think that's what we see falling off.
而对于后面的事情 提到这些都是很重要的 因为我觉得这就是那些脱落的东西
From this angle also notice that if you look straight up
从这个角度也能注意到 如果你直接向上看
it does look like the flame. There's a bit of smoke in the air.
它看起来确实像是火焰(的影响) 空气中还有一点烟
I'm not sure if that's significant.
我不知道这是否是重要的
We're not sure if it's because it's perhaps running a little more fuel rich for throttle reasons.
我们不知道这是否是因为它为了节流而使用了富燃的混合比
Frankly we don't know very much but yeah at this point it is a fairly long ascent
坦率地说 我们还不太清楚 但没错 在这时 SN9在进行一个相对耗时的上升段飞行
where they deactivate the engines one by one until they reach apogee.
在这段飞行过程中 发动机一个接一个地被关闭 直到远地点
Apogee being when SN9 gets as high as it's gonna get
远地点是指SN9到达最高点的时候
and that on this flight happened around (T+)4:20.
而到达远地点的时刻为(T+)4:20左右
So this was about 10 kilometers up and by this point it's only flying on a single Raptor engine
那么这差不多是在10公里的高空 此时它只用一台猛禽发动机在飞行
enough to just keep it going at the velocity it was when all the others shut down.
足以让它在其他发动机都关机的情况下保持速度
So it cuts that off and then proceeds to go into the belly flop maneuver.
那么SN9的这台发动机也关机了 然后继续进行机腹向下俯冲的动作
In this case they overcooked it just a bit.
这次 他们做得有点过火了
Now we weren't sure about the camera angles on this.
那么我们不太确定摄像机的拍摄角度
But it definitely looked like the nose goes down
但它看起来肯定是机头向下的
because if you look at other camera angles it seems to confirm this.
因为如果你看其他的拍摄角度 似乎可以证实这一点
But then they use aerodynamics.
但是他们使用了空气动力(来进行姿态的调整)
They increase the drag on the nose fins by folding them further out and the rear fins get folded in.
增加机头翼面的阻力 让它们展得更开 而尾部翼面收得更紧
And they bring it down to the horizontal belly flop maneuver.
然后SN9的机腹放平 (完成)机腹向下机动
So this of course maximizes the drag
那么这当然会使阻力最大化
and sets the terminal velocity initially it's about 300 400 kilometers per hour.
并设定了终端速度 最初的速度大约是每小时300到400千米
But as they descend into the thicker parts of the atmosphere,
但当SN9下降到大气层较厚的部分时
it drops down to about 250 kilometers per hour.
速度会下降到大约每小时250公里
I love these shots showing the finns actuating to control the descent.
我喜欢这些显示了翼面工作 控制航天器下降的镜头
But the camera froze. Typical.
但是画面卡住了 老卡顿了
But look the good news for this flight is the transition from the vertical to the horizontal
但注意到这个飞行的好消息是 从垂直到水平的过渡
and controlling the belly flop were really good.
和(这部分的)机腹向下俯冲的控制都非常好
It was consistent which means those were the things I had the biggest concern about.
这与SN8的表现一致 而这些是我最担心的事情
Oddly enough I haven't had huge concerns about the reliability of the Raptors.
奇怪的是 我对猛禽的可靠性并没有太大的担忧
Although given what happened next I'm perhaps beginning to reassess that situation.
虽然鉴于接下来发生的事情 我或许要开始重新评估这种情况
So they're supposed to light up two Raptors and only one of the Raptors lights.
那么他们应该启动两台猛禽 但只有一台猛禽点火了
The second one it just coughs it splutters and we end up going into fireball mode.
第二只猛禽只是咳嗽 发出PUI PUI声 而最终进入火球模式
Okay so let's look at this in quarter speed.
好了 让我们用四分之一的速度来看看这个片段
One thing to notice first of all is the nose by now is covered in frost
首先要注意的是机鼻上已经布满了霜
because of course that's where the oxygen header tank is.
当然因为那是氧气头部储箱的位置
You can see the two vents coming out to the sides.
你可以看到航天器的两侧正排出气体
Those are from the engine chill system I believe.
我想那是发动机冷却系统的排气口
So as it gets close to the ground, it's falling at about 70 to 80 meters per second.
那么当它接近地面时 它以每秒70到80米的速度下降
And it starts to go to light up the engine.
然后开始启动发动机
So the important thing to note is that the first engine comes on and starts generating really good mach diamond.
那么最重要的是 第一台发动机启动后 开始产生非常好的马赫环
So there's the ignition and you get a nice rocket-like flame.
那么这就是点火 你能看到一个漂亮的火箭般的火焰
The second one goes up and it doesn't do that at all.
第二台发动机也在点火 但完全没点起来
So note that the first engine keeps producing these good mac diamonds
所以请注意 第一台发动机一直在产生这些好的马赫环
which is an indication of good thrust all the way through.
这表明它一直在产生良好的推力
It flares a bit here and there but it then recovers
它(身上)也在到处喷火 但随后就恢复了
so that engine is good all the way down.
所以那台发动机一直都是好的
There's no failure going on there but the other engine fails to light.
这台发动机没出问题 但另一台发动机却无法点火
which says to me that there may be a problem with that specific Raptor on the relight.
我觉得 可能只是那台猛禽发动机存在无法再次点火的问题
It wasn't a vehicle issue or it's most likely not a vehicle issue.
这不是航天器的问题 或者说很可能不是航天器的问题
It's certainly not the low pressure any specific fuel or oxidizer system.
肯定不是燃料或者氧化剂系统的低压问题
But it's something that affects that engine and not the other one.
但可能会是只影响这台发动机而不是那台的问题
Maybe there's a void or a bubble in the tank that went and caused the engine to stutter and fail.
也许储罐里存在空隙或者气泡 导致发动机的卡顿和故障
We're not sure. We'll have to get more data.
我们还不确定 我们必须得到更多的数据
Now there's other things to see from this angle.
从这个角度还可以看到其他的东西
First of all, there's a couple of items that are seen to get blown out during this.
首先 有几件东西看上去在这期间被炸掉了
And as far as we can tell they are much lighter.
据我们所知 它们的重量要轻得多
So there's the first one shooting off to the left.
那么第一个是向左边射过去的东西
And it's getting caught up in the air.
它被空气托举起来了
We actually see that it falls slower than the rest of the vehicle.
我们可以看到它的坠落速度比航天器的其他部分都要慢
The second one is falling off to the right and off to the top.
第二个则是向右和(画面)上部的脱落的
So we think these are just shielding
那么 我们认为这些只是(热)屏蔽材料
that is inside the skirt to protect things like composite overwrapped pressure vessels.
也就是安装在裙板内的东西 是为了保护像缠绕复合材料压力容器这样的东西
things that wouldn't react too well to too much heat.
这些东西比较怕过多的热量
In fact if you watch this pass enough
事实上 如果你充分地观看这个片段
you'll actually start to see the second thing bouncing around inside the skirt before it's blown out.
其实你会开始看到第二个东西在吹出去之前 在裙板内跳来跳去
But yeah if the other thing to watch is the engine that's failing slightly.
但是 是的 如果还有另一件事情要注意 那就是轻微故障的那台发动机
At this point you can actually see there's flames at the base of that engine or the head
这时其实你可以看到在那台发动机的基部或者说头部有火焰
because we're looking at it from below.
因为我们是从下面看的
So the power head is very likely falling apart.
所以发动机的动力头很可能是散架了
So this is very much looking like an engine failing and coming apart
那么这看起来很像是一台发动机发生了故障而解体了
and the question is
而问题是
was it a flaw in the engine? Did it just break because it'd been run for too long?
是发动机的缺陷吗？还是说运行时间太长而出了问题？
Or was there something in the system feeding it
或者说是推进剂供应系统供应了什么东西
because yeah if you have a void in a pipe and it is being pumped hard enough into the engine
因为是的 如果你的管道内有空气 而被足够有力地泵到了发动机里
when that hits your pump or hits the impellers
当它打到你的泵或打到涡轮的时候
RUD = Rapid Unscheduled Disassembly，快速意外解体
it can damage your turbo pump destroy it and result in an RUD that looks very much like this.
它可能会损坏你的涡轮泵 并导致一个看起来很像这次爆炸的RUD
And we should point out this is very distinct from what happened on SN8.
我们要指出的是 这与SN8的情况截然不同
In that case the Starship had a fuel supply problem.
那次Starship的燃料供应有问题
Pressure was too low.
压力太低
The oxygen get fed into the engines.
(过量)氧气进入发动机
And we got this bright green flame of engine rich exhaust
而我们看到了富发动机燃烧的 明亮的绿色火焰
as the engine destroyed itself due to a failure in Starship.
因为Starship内部(储罐)的问题 破坏了发动机
This could be a failure of the engine most likely
而SN9很可能就是发动机的故障
but it could be something that only affects that engine in Starship fuel supply.
但也可能是Starship燃料供应(系统)中 只影响到的那台发动机的部分
So we'll have to wait to find out what really happened here I suspect.
所以我觉得我们得等着看看到底发生了什么
Now while SpaceX is no doubt going to be doing their own internal analysis.
那么虽然SpaceX无疑会进行内部的分析
The community are already out there, sleuthing in the way that a bunch of Texas tank watchers only can.
但(爱好者)社区已经在外面进行调查了 一群德克萨斯州的储罐观察者才会做的事情
So we have RGV Aerial photography
那么我们有了RGV航拍的图像
who pretty much arranged a flyover as soon as the airspace restrictions were lifted.
刚在空域限制被取消后 就安排了飞越
And this is a very different scene to SN8 where we had very large chunks visible on the pad.
而这里就与SN8的情况有了很大不同 着陆场上能看到很多大块
The stuff is spread all over the place.
这些东西散落在各处
The vehicle hit at a much higher speed
(因为)航天器以更高的速度进行了撞击
and if you look at some of the other angles you'll see the the debris is flying off in every direction.
而如果你看到了一些其他的角度 你会看到 碎片是飞向各个方向的
We actually know how fast it hit.
我们实际上知道它撞击的速度有多快
Because of course flightclub.io has been out there analyzing everybody's pictures
当然 flightclub.io已经分析了每个人的视频画面
and trying to figure out the altitude the speed the velocity doing the math.
并试图计算出高度 速度
So that everybody else can figure out what what was really going on
这样其他人就能弄清楚到底发生了什么事
and according to this yeah it's a free fall velocity right at the point
根据这个分析 没错 此刻达到了自由落体的速度
where it was firing the engine was probably about 80 meters per second
SN9刚点火的时候大概是每秒80米的速度
when it lit its engine and started to decelerate.
也是刚开始减速的时候
It could have hit the ground whoa say about 69 meters per second.
SN9撞击地面的速度大概为每秒69米的速度
Of course by this point with SN8 we knew exactly what went on because Elon told everyone on Twitter
当然在SN8的时候 此时我们就知道到底发生了什么 因为马一龙在推特上告诉了大家
but right now he's decided he's taking a Twitter break.
但现在他决定离开推特一段时间
So we're left to look at pictures watch explosions
所以我们只能看视频画面 看爆炸了
and maybe when the sun rises over Boca Chica,
而也许当太阳(再)从博卡奇卡上空升起的时候
we might get a few more clues from the debris left laying around.
我们可能会从着陆场周围的残骸上面 得到更多的线索
SpaceX will have to have their own investigation.
SpaceX将不得不进行自己的调查
They'll have to satisfy the FAA that they understand what went wrong and how they're going to remedy it.
他们必须让FAA满意 让他们明白出了什么问题 以及他们将如何补救
And only then are they going to get to fly SN10 which is sitting out there.
只有这样 他们才能让SN10试飞 而SN10就在那里竖立着
And that's assuming the SN10 wasn't damaged by being in close proximity to SN9.
而这(只)是假设SN10没有因为靠近SN9而受损
Perhaps this is SpaceX engineer's way of incentivizing SN10 to do as it's told.
也许这是SpaceX工程师给SN10训话的方式
Otherwise its fate might be similar.
否则它的命运可能也会相似
Either way I wish it the best of luck.
不管怎样 我都祝它好运
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全